(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-26T16:50:50.173358",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
まーす！
Welcome!
おはようございます！
Good morning!
ということで、
So,
一級船舶免許を取ってからなんと1年が経ちました！
It's been a whole year since I got my class-1 boat license!
大空スバルです！
I'm Oozora Subaru!
今回はロケに来ております！
We're out on location today!
ゲストはミオしゃ～！
Our guest is Mio-sha!
はーい！
Hi!
うしうし、うしだよ！大神ミオだよ！
Ushi-ushi, it's Ushi! Ookami Mio!
ホロライブゲーマーズの大神ミオです！
Hololive Gamers' Ookami Mio!
今日は呼んでくれてありがとう！
Thanks for having me today!
いや呼ばれたは呼ばれたけど…今日何をするんでしょうか？
Well, you called me, but... what are we doing today?
今日の企画言っちゃっていいわけ？
Can I just blurt out today's project?
おお、じゃあ言っちゃってもらって…
Oh, go right ahead then...
じゃあ参ります！
Here we go!
大空スバル、いざ大海原へ！ミオしゃを海のドライブに連れて行く！
Oozora Subaru's Voyage to the High Seas: Taking Mio-sha on a Marine Drive!
ええ！？大空クルーズ第1号のお客様がミオしゃに決定しました！
Eh?! Mio-sha has been chosen as the very first customer for the Oozora Cruise!
ガチで怖いから…ガチで…
That's genuinely terrifying... seriously...
いや、大丈夫大丈夫！ガチ免許あるから免許！
No, it's fine! I seriously have a license!
シオンと取った免許あるから大丈夫、大丈夫！
I got it with Shion, so it's totally fine!
免許取りたての運転ほど怖いことねえじゃん！
There's nothing scarier than driving right after getting a license!
いや、しかも一応スバル、個人的にちゃんと運転しに行ってるから！
Besides, I've actually gone out driving on my own, you know!
あ、練習済みってこと？
Oh, you mean you've practiced?
そう！練習もしてきたから、任せてよ！
Yeah! I've practiced, so leave it to me!
学科の成績良かった！
My written test scores were great!
スバルさん、ミオしゃと言えば釣りでしょ？いや、そんな事ないからね！
Subaru, when you think of Mio-sha, it's fishing, right? No, not at all!
ミオしゃと言えば釣りだから！
When you think of Mio-sha, it's fishing!
釣りしてさ、うめえ魚でも食おうよ！
Let's go fishing and eat some delicious fish!
おおお、じゃあ今日は船釣りするってこと？そう、船釣りをします！
Ooh, so we're doing boat fishing today? Yep, boat fishing!
なんかスバル免許取ったんですけど、船の運転は本当に危なくて…
I got my license and all, but driving a boat is seriously dangerous...
やめてよ！不安になるような事言うの…
Stop it! Don't say things that make me anxious...
マジで本当に死りたくなかったら今日見張り手伝って欲しい本当に！
Seriously, if you don't want to die today, I really need you to help keep watch!
怖いよ！
That's terrifying!
船の事故って結構多いんだって！そうなんだ～！
Boat accidents apparently happen quite a bit! Is that so?!
だから海に入る以上、安全についてもしっかりと学ばないといけない！という事で今回はなんと、
So since we're going out on the water, we have to learn about safety properly! And so, this time...
海上保安庁さんのご協力いただいております！ええ！？海上保安庁！？
We've received cooperation from the Japan Coast Guard! Eh?! The Coast Guard?!
海の安全について色々教えてくれるみたいなので早速行ってみよう！
They're going to teach us all about marine safety, so let's check it out!
ということで、今回ご協力いただく秋山さんです！
And now, introducing our collaborator for today, Akiyama-san!
よろしくお願いします！よろしくお願いします！千葉海上保安部の秋山です。
Nice to meet you! Nice to meet you! I'm Akiyama from the Chiba Coast Guard Department.
今日は一緒に勉強していきましょう！
Let's study together today!
おー！よろしくお願いします！
Yeah! Looking forward to it!
今日はね、なんと船の運転にあたって色々教えていただける聞いたんですけどよろしくお願いします！
Today, we heard you're going to teach us various things about driving a boat. We look forward to it!
海を安全に楽しむためのポイントをクイズを交えてご紹介させていただきたいと思います！教えてもらえるってことか！
I'd like to introduce points for enjoying the sea safely through a quiz! Oh, you'll teach us through a quiz?
ちょっと待ってミオしゃ聞いた？クイズだって！クイズやばいんだけど！
Wait a second, did you hear that, Mio-sha? A quiz! A quiz is bad news!
ちょっと待ってでもうちは何も知らないよ？
Wait a minute, but I don't know anything about this!
もしかしてスバルだけが答えるってコト？
Does that mean only Subaru has to answer?
なんて一緒に協力しようって気はないの？お前！当事者意識！当事者意識！
Why don't you have any intention of cooperating?! You! Have some skin in the game!
舐めかもしれない…当事者意識持ってよ！申し訳ないけどさ…
Maybe I'm underestimating this... You need to take responsibility! Sorry, but...
見忘れないんだこれ…
I can't overlook this...
え、見忘れないの？え、見忘れない？
Eh, you can't overlook it? Eh, you won't?
だってスバルがちゃんと答えて皆さんに伝えるってことですよね？つまり
Because Subaru will answer properly and convey it to everyone, right? In other words...
はいそうです！やべえ！やべえよ！
Yes, that's correct! Oh no! This is bad!
それでは秋山さんよろしくお願いします！よろしくお願いします！
Well then, Akiyama-san, please take care of us! Looking forward to it!
お勉強開始！
Studies begin!
日本の領土は、約38万km²で世界61位の面積だが領海と漁業と天然資源の開発等の主权的権利がある
Japan's territory is about 380,000 km², ranking 61st globally, but including its exclusive economic zone with sovereign rights over
排他的経済水域の面積は約447万km²であり世界でも10位以内の面積を誇る。海上保安庁はこの広大なエリアを11の管区に分け、約15,000人で24時間365日守り続けている！
territorial waters, fishing, and natural resources, the area is ~4.47 million km², ranking in the top 10. The Coast Guard protects this vast area divided into 11 jurisdictions with ~15,000 personnel 24/7!
やばいじゃん！
That's insane!
だからさ、日本って島国じゃん！周りに海がいっぱいあるからってことですよね？
Exactly, Japan's an island nation! Because there's ocean all around us, right?
そうです。海上保安庁はこの広大なエリアを11の管区に分けて、海上保安官約15,000人で24時間365日守り続けています！
Correct. The Coast Guard protects this vast area divided into 11 jurisdictions with about 15,000 officers, 24/7, 365 days a year!
ええ、凄いよ！15,000人だけなんだよ？っていうか…
Whoa, that's amazing! Only 15,000 people? I mean...
海上保安庁は少ない人数で頑張っているので、スバルさん、よかったら海上保安官になりませんか！
The Coast Guard is working hard with limited personnel. Subaru-san, would you like to become a Coast Guard officer?
ええ！？入っちゃおうかな！入っちゃおうかな！スカウトされてる！YAGOOバイバイ！俺海上保安官になる！
Eh?! Maybe I should join! I'm getting scouted! Bye-bye YAGOO! I'm becoming a Coast Guard officer!
大丈夫そうかな？結構ポンコツですよ？忘れ物とか結構スゴイ…
Will she be okay? She's quite scatterbrained, you know? She forgets things a lot...
ちょっと忘れものとか結構すごいんですけど大丈夫ですかね？すぐ忘れちゃうんですけど…
I tend to forget things quite a bit, will I be okay? I forget stuff right away...
どういう人が適性があるんですか？
What kind of person is suited for the job?
スバルさんのように真面目な方なら大丈夫です！
Someone serious and dedicated like Subaru-san would do fine!
え！真面目なんだ！まじ？
Eh, I'm serious?! Seriously?
次は楽しいはずの海でのレジャーが悲しい事故にならないように自分の命を救うための3つの基本を紹介します。まず1つ目がライフジャケットの常時着用です。万が一船から海に落ちてしまった場合ライフジャケットを着用しているだけで着用していない人と比べると助かる確率が4倍にもなります。ですので海でマリンレジャーを楽しむ際にはライフジャケットの常時着用をお願いします。
Next, we'll introduce 3 basics to save your life so that fun marine leisure doesn't turn into a tragic accident. First is the constant wearing of life jackets. In the unlikely event you fall overboard, wearing a life jacket quadruples your chances of survival compared to not wearing one. Therefore, please wear a life jacket at all times when enjoying marine leisure.
ただしライフジャケットを正しく着用していても脱げてしまったり、古いものを使い続けているとうまく膨らまなかったりしますので、正しい着用と定期的な点検を心掛けてくださいね！
However, even if worn correctly, old or ill-fitting life jackets might not inflate properly if they slip off or are outdated. So please ensure correct usage and regular inspections!
はい！分かりました！
Yes! Understood!
次は携帯電話等の連絡手段の確保です。皆さんは普段の生活の中でスマートフォンを持ち歩いていると思うのですが、海でもこれが非常に重要となります。海での事故に遭ってしまった場合、海上保安庁などの救助機関にいち早く連絡することが重要なのですが、スマートフォンを海に落としてしまって通報できないといったことも多いためこのようにストラップ付きの防水パックで持ち歩くことが大切なんです。
Next is securing communication devices like mobile phones. You all probably carry smartphones in daily life, and this becomes extremely important at sea. If you encounter a marine accident, contacting rescue agencies like the Coast Guard as quickly as possible is vital. However, since people often drop their phones in the ocean and can't make calls, carrying them in waterproof pouches with straps is crucial.
おお～！
Ooh~!
最後…
And finally...
警察には110番
For police, it's 110,
消防には119番といった番号と同様に
and for fire departments, it's 119.
海上保安庁にも
Similarly, the Japan Coast Guard
緊急通報用の電話番号があるのですが
has an emergency contact number.
皆さんご存知ですか？
Does everyone know it?
えー知らなかった！ウチは！
Eh, we didn't know!
スバル知ってるこれ！
Subaru knows this!
一級小型船舶をお持ちのスバルさんなら当然知っていると思います。
Naturally, as a small vessel license holder, Subaru-san knows.
やばい圧ヤバイ...
The pressure is insane...
おーみんな！
Hey everyone!
海の事件・事故は118番！
Marine incidents and accidents are 118!
すごいです！正解です！
Amazing! That's correct!
おーよかった！やったー！
Yay! Awesome!
ここからは本格的に
From here on, we'll officially
何問かクイズを出題していきたい！
pose a few quiz questions!
やばい！さっきの序章だったんだって！
Wait, that was just the introduction!
え！そうなの！？
Eh? Is that so?!
がっつりクイズかと思ってたら
I thought that was the main quiz!
これから海に出るスバルさんに
To Subaru-san, who is heading out to sea,
海上交通のルールについて質問です！
I have a question about maritime traffic rules.
はい！
Here!
こちらにスバルさんが操船している船と
On the left is Subaru-san's vessel crossing paths,
右側にミオさんが乗っている船があります。
and on the right is Mio-san's vessel.
このままではぶつかってしまう恐れがあるため
Since they might collide if they keep going,
スバルさんが取るべき行動は次のうちどれでしょう？
what action should Subaru-san take?
みおちゃん分かるわけ。
Mio-chan, I know this!
この距離感だったら急げばいける！みたいな感じになりそうじゃない？
If this is a close call, can't we just speed up and make it through?
ふはは！そんなわけないだろ！
No way!
なんだそのふははは！
What's with that "fu haha"?
これスバルね、これね、船舶免許で勉強したことある。これ知ってる？
Subaru, you know this because you studied for the small vessel license, right?
知ってたよねえ。
I thought so!
これは4番、右に舵を切り相手を避けるです！
It's number 4: Turn right and avoid the other ship!
正解は4番です！
The correct answer is number 4!
おー！そうなのんだ！
Ooh! That's it!
このような状況では海上衝突予防法という法律によって相手を右に見る船舶が相手を避ける必要があるんです。
In such situations, under the Act on Prevention of Collisions at Sea, a vessel seeing another on its right must give way.
この場合はスバルさんの船が右に舵を切って避けるか、原則または停止してミオさんの船を避けるのが正解になります。
In this case, it's correct for Subaru-san's ship to turn right to avoid it, or slow down/stop to let Mio-san's ship pass.
スバルこういう時も怖いから止まっちゃいます。
Subaru, I'd get scared in situations like this and just stop.
先に行ってください！
Go ahead!
あーでも止まってもいいってことですもんね？
Ah, but stopping is also allowed, right?
そうです。
That's right.
次の問題！
Next question!
ここに架空の湾、スバル湾があります。
Here we have a fictitious "Subaru Bay."
船が入港するためにはスバル航路を通って入港します。
For a ship to enter, it passes through the "Subaru Channel."
航路のここに設置される航路標識の組み合わせをこの中からお答えください。
Please answer how the channel markers placed here are combined.
船舶免許持ってるので分かります！
I have a small vessel license, so I know!
おー！
Ooh!
これは右舷標識と左舷標識なので、赤い三角形の方が右で、緑の四角の方が左側に入ります。で上も一緒のように入ります。
This is about lateral marks, so the red triangle is on the right, and the green square is on the left, and the top one is the same.
へー！
Hee-hee!
スバルさん、さすがです！
Subaru-san, as expected!
よっしゃー！
Yay!
あぶねー！
That was close.
ちゃんと分かってた！
You actually got it right!
あたりまえじゃん！
Well, obviously!
では、次の問題です。
Now, for the next question.
次の問題！
Next question!
ここに航路標識を設置して船に対して標識の西側は安全に走りますよということを示したいのですが、
We want to indicate that channel markers are placed here and the west side is safe to navigate.
その場合この4つのうちのどれを設置すればいいと思いますか？
in that case, which of these four should be placed?
やばいよみおちゃん...
Oh no, Mio-chan...
これはちょっと難しいよ。
This is a bit difficult.
ウチは全然さっぱり0%分かりませんけど。
I have no clue, 0% idea!
ででも、多分一番右のやつだった気がします。
Well, I think it's probably the one on the far right.
え、その心は？
Eh, what about the heart?
その心は、なんか一番右に置いてあるやつが西なんだよ。
The heart is that the one placed furthest right is west.
いー！
Hee-hee!
で上々ってなってるやつが下で下下が南で、こうなんかダイヤマークみたいになってるやつが東なんじゃないかな。
And the ones stacked top-top mean bottom-bottom, which is south, and the diamond-like one means east, maybe?
なるほど方向を表してるってこと？
I see, it indicates directions?
そう。だから多分一番右！
So probably the far right!
スバルさん、正解です！
Subaru-san, that's correct!
あぶない！あぶない！
Close! Close!
ちゃんと分かってるやん。
You really understand this!
もう海上保安庁さんで間違えたら免許剥奪されちまう！
If you get this wrong with the Coast Guard, your license would be revoked!
そうだなの。
That's true.
この航ロ標識は方位標識と呼ばれるもので、それぞれの標識の東・南・北側に安全に走れる場所があるということを示しています。
These channel markers are called cardinal marks, and they indicate that there is a safe place to run on the east, west, south, or north side of each marker.
おー！
Ooh!
本格的なクイズで海難防止について勉強してきましたが
We've learned about preventing marine disasters through serious quizzes,
船の事故についてもご紹介させてください！
but let's also introduce ship accidents.
うん。
Mm.
令和7年に海上保安庁が取り扱った船の事故は1711隻であり、そのうち、約半数の833隻がプレジャーボートでの事故となっています。
In Reiwa 7, ship accidents handled by the Japan Coast Guard numbered 1,711, of which about half, 833, were pleasure boat accidents.
プレジャーボートって何？
What's a pleasure boat?
なんかスバルの乗れるすごいみんなで遊んだりとかするやつ！
Like something Subaru can ride on, to have fun with everyone!
釣りしたりとか観光用の船みたいな？
Or for sightseeing or similar ships?
そう。
Right.
この事故のうち約7割が船の整備不良や見張り不十分といった人為的要因と呼ばれる事故となっているんです。
Of these accidents, about 70% are due to human factors such as poor maintenance or insufficient lookouts.
プレジャーボートを操船する方は出港前点検・適切な見張りの実施を行い事故を未然に防ぎましょう！
Those operating pleasure boats should conduct pre-departure checks and proper lookouts to prevent accidents in advance.
はい！
Right!
出港前点検の実施はプレジャーボートの事故では機関故障が多くを占める。二次災害に繋がる恐れがあるため必ず行おう！船が動かなくなったことによって流されて浅瀬に乗り上げてしまったり、他の船にぶつかって二次災害に繋がることもあることから出港前点検は必ず実施して船を適切に管理しましょう。
Pre-departure checks are crucial because engine trouble accounts for many pleasure boat accidents, which can lead to secondary disasters like being swept away to shallow waters or colliding with other vessels, so always perform them and properly maintain your boat.
はい！
Right!
そして見張りの実施が安全運行の基本です。意味は広く他の船とぶつかってしまう恐れはないと思われがちなんですけれども、見張り不十分による船同士の衝突は多くを発生しているんです。船長だけではなくミオさんのように船に乗っている人たちにも常に見張りを行って事故を防いでください。
And conducting a proper lookout is the basis of safe navigation; while it may seem there's no risk of collision, insufficient lookouts cause many collisions, so not just the captain, but everyone on board should keep a lookout to prevent accidents.
ウチも見てなきゃいけないってコト？
So we have to keep watch too?
当たり前じゃん！
Obviously!
〇にたくなかったら見張りしてないとな、さ
If you don't want to [censored], you gotta keep watch, or else...
こええ！
Scary!
でも見張りは本当に大事ってめちゃめちゃ言われたから！めちゃんこ大事ですよね？
They told us keeping watch is super important, so it's super important, right?
はい、とても大切です。
Yes, very important!
見張りの基本は、全方位にあたり、
The basics of keeping watch are maintaining a constant all-round lookout...
対象物を特定せず、継続的に繰り返して行うことが重要です。
without focusing on a specific target, and repeating it continuously.
ふむふむ。
I see...
じゃあウチも見張り頑張ります！
Well then, I'll do my best to keep watch too!
頑張ってね！
Good luck!
という事で！
With that said!
今回ご協力いただいた海上保安庁の秋山さん、本当にありがとうございました！
A huge thank you to Mr. Akiyama from the Coast Guard for helping us today!
ありがとうございました！
Thank you so much!
Thank you very much!
いっぱい釣れるといいですね！行ってらっしゃい！
I hope you catch lots of fish! Have a safe trip!
行ってきます！いっぱい釣るぞ！！
We're heading out! We're gonna catch so many!
釣るぞ、釣るぞ！
Let's go, let's go!
という事で、乗船しました！
And with that, we've boarded!
え、これ、これがスバルの船…？
Is this Subaru's boat...?
そう、これがスバルの船らしいです。
Yeah, apparently this is Subaru's boat.
なんか結構デカくてビビってます！
It's pretty big and I'm totally spooked!
いや、デカくてビビってるってことはこれレンタルだよね、たぶん。
Wait, if it's so big that you're spooked, this is a rental, right?
いや、そうだよ。これレンタルしてきました。
Yeah, that's right. We rented this.
今回はですね、セントラルさんの東京ワンフィッシングに参加します！
Today we're joining Central Tokyo Fishing!
わあー！
Wow!
木更津沖から気軽に楽しめるフィッシングプランで、なんとね、ベテランスタッフさんのサポートを受けながらボートフィッシングが楽しめるということで、
It's a fishing plan where you can easily enjoy boat fishing off Kisarazu with support from veteran staff!
それは安心だね！
That sounds reassuring!
ところがどっこい！
However!
普段はですねスタッフさんが操縦するんですけど、今回は許可をいただいたので、スバルが運転します！
Normally the staff handles the steering, but we got permission today, so Subaru is going to drive!
いー！
Yay!
それはでもあの…釣りをするってことだよね？
Wait, that means... you're gonna actually fish, right?
そうだよ、今日は釣りをします。
Yep, we're going fishing today.
なんかポイントとか分かってるわけ？
Do you even know the good spots?
分かんない！だからね、スタッフさんに教えてもらおうと思う！
Nope, I have no clue! So I'm gonna have the staff teach me!
なるほどね！
Makes sense!
ちなみに今回はね、シロギスっていうのを釣るらしい。
By the way, today we're supposed to catch Japanese whiting!
ったことある？
Have you ever caught one?
ない！
Nope!
入れ食いらしい！
Apparently they're super easy to catch!
入れ食い！？
Super easy?!
信じてるぞ！
I'm counting on you!
本当かなぁ？信じてるぞ、セントラルさん！
Can we really trust that? Central-san!
まあ、行ってみましょうよ！
Well, let's go check it out!
はい！
Right!
という事で、出発準備OK！ミオしゃ準備はいいか？
Alright, departure prep is good! Mio, are you ready?
いつでも行くぞ！
I'm ready whenever!
それでは、大空スバル号、出航！出航！
Then, the Oozora Subaru号, set sail! Set sail!
行くぞ！
Let's go!
運転できるのか本当に？
Can we really drive this?
まずゆっくり発進。
First, slowly accelerate.
やべえ！軽い！
Oh crap, it's light!
軽い…？
Light...?
8、9、10…やべえめっちゃ軽い！ちょっと待って！
8, 9, 10... Oh crap, it's super light! Wait, wait, wait!
大丈夫だから！大丈夫だから！
It's okay, I'm okay! Because I'm okay!
このままだと…
At this rate...
前方の船に突っ込みそうな感じだけど大丈夫？左から回っていきます。
We're gonna crash right into the boat ahead of us, aren't we? We'll turn left to go around!
そうですね。
Right, good idea.
おーー、やべえめっちゃ軽い！
Whoa, it's super light!
軽いと何か問題が？
What happens when it's light?
軽いと…うん。ギュウウンって加速する！
When it's light... it accelerates really fast!
あ、なるほどね。
Oh, I see!
うわー！うわー！なにこの揺れ！
Whoa! What is this shaking?!
やべえすぐ30出るやん！
We're already hitting 30 knots!
やばっ！すごい！めっちゃ曲がる！
Whoa, it turns so sharply!
操縦しやすいってこと？
Does that mean it's easy to steer?
ちょっと慣れないかも！
I might not be used to it yet!
慣れてない。もっと慣れていく。
You'll get used to it soon.
うねうねある。やべえ！
There are buoys everywhere! Oh crap!
ゆっくり。
Slow down.
〇にたくなかったら見張ってくれ！
If you don't want to [censored], keep watch!
やばい、つかまる、つかまる！
Hold on, hold on!
なんか前方に何かでっかいの浮いてる。
Wait, there's a huge thing ahead!
でっかいの浮いてる？
Something's floating?
なんか浮いてる。何あれ？
What on earth is that?
前のさ、船がいるじゃん。
There's a boat right in front of us.
はい。
Right.
あの船がさ、同じ方向に行こうとしてるんだけどさ、
That boat is trying to go in the same direction, but you know...
確かにねえ。
True!
船の後ろも行っちゃダメだからさ、追い抜いた方がいいんだけどさ、
You shouldn't go behind other boats either, so we should overtake them, but...
スバルにそんな度胸はない！
Subaru doesn't have the nerve for that!
うわーー！すげえ持ってかれる！
Whoa, it's getting pulled!
すげえ曲がる！めっちゃ持ってかれてるよ！
It turns so sharply! It's really getting pulled!
海運転ムズイ！
Navigating the ocean is tough!
持ってかれる？
Getting pulled?
よく分かんねえ方に曲がる。
It turns in weird directions.
潮の流れとかがあるのかな…？
Is it because of the ocean currents or something...?
でも確かに、スバル今までこんなに波立ってるこでこんなデカイの運転したことないかも。
To be fair, I've never driven anything this big in such choppy waters before.
意外と波は立ってるんですか、船長？
Are the waves actually pretty high, Captain?
まあ、体感だいぶ立ってますね、これ。
Well, I'd say they're quite high, yeah.
あ、そうなんだ。
Oh, is that right?
どうよ、スバル船長の運転は？
How's my driving, Captain?
まだ不安はあるけど…
I still have my doubts, but...
まあこの調子であれば、事故りはしなさそう。
at this rate, we probably won't crash!
スバルビビリだからな！
Cuz Subaru's a coward!
もうやばいってなったらエンジン止めるから。
If things get dangerous, I'll just stop the engine!
エンジン切っちゃうんだ。
You'll just cut the engine?
うん、もう「あの避けてください」のスタンスでいくから。
Yeah, I'll go with the "please avoid us" stance.
なるほどね！
Makes sense!
うーーん！
Whoa!
多分、スピード出した方が揺れ少ない気がする。
Actually, going faster probably makes it shake less.
いや、それはそう！
Well, that's true!
それはそうなんだけどさ！
That's true, but...
あの船を抜かすまでは、何があるか分からん！
until we pass that boat, you never know what might happen!
いや、そうね、あの船ちょっと怖いね。
Yeah, that's true, that boat is a bit scary.
いや、この「間通る系」苦手なんだよ！マジで。
Man, I'm really bad at passing between things! Seriously.
心理ストレスがやばい！！
The psychological stress is insane!
なんかあの船あそこ曲がろうとしている気がする。
Wait, looks like that boat is about to turn there.
確かに右側にちょっとずつ。
True, it's shifting a bit to the right.
そうだよね。
That's true.
じゃあどうですか、初海？
So, what are your thoughts on your first time at sea?
こええ。
Scary!
こわい？
Scary?
なんかこんなにいっぱい船がいる所知らない。
I didn't know there were so many boats out here!
俺今まで家の庭でずっと走ってたんや。
Up until now, I've just been driving around my backyard!
じゃあ結構緊張感あるね！
So there's quite a bit of tension!
緊張感あるよ！
There's totally tension!
ミオしゃあれ！
Mio, look at that!
うん。
Hm?
あれ、さっき習ったやつ！
That's what we learned about earlier!
あーー！あれ、V、V！
Oh, right, the V thing!
あれよ、海上保安庁さんがつけてくれてるんや。まあ、ありがと。
Look, the Coast Guard set that up for us! Well, thanks!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
うおーー！海に出る！
Whoa, we're out in the open ocean!
うおーー！
Whoa!
やべえ！ガチで海じゃん！！
Whoa, this is the real ocean!!
ちょっと待って、やばすぎ！
Wait, this is way too crazy!
海だ～！
It's the ocean!
着いたぜ！
We made it!
こんだけ広かったら安心感あるんじゃない？
Doesn't it feel reassuring when it's this wide?
あるある！
Totally!
初めてこんなレーダーみたいな見たわ。
It's my first time seeing a radar like this.
おーー。
Ooooh.
あの辺じゃね？
Must be around here, right?
お、この辺だ！
Oh, it's around here!
ポイント到着！
Point reached!
もういいのかな、始めて。
Can we start already?
始めて。行くぞ！
Let's do it!
釣り開始！！
Fishing start!
それで、底に着くのを待つ。
Now we wait for it to hit the bottom.
着いたかも！
I think it reached!
着いたかな？
Did it?
あ、着いた！
Ah, it reached!
「トン」って感じした！
It felt like a little "tap"!
あとはズルズルと引きずる。
Now we just drag it along smoothly.
するとシロギスという釣れるらしい。
Apparently, if you do that, you can catch Japanese whiting.
本当かなぁ？
Really?
なんか突かれてる感覚あるよ！
I feel something poking me!
本当は？
Really?
なんかツンツンされてる。
It feels like it's being gently tapped.
餌だけ食われてねぇかな？
I wonder if only the bait is being eaten?
どうなんだろうね。
I wonder how it is.
シロギスって頭いいのかな？
Are Japanese whiting smart, I wonder?
食い逃げされてたらどうしよう。
What if it gets stolen away?
でもちっちゃいから脳みそちっちゃいんじゃないの？
But they're small, so their brains must be small too, right?
ミオしゃ刺すね～！
Mio, you're sharp!
ちなみにアジ釣りに行った時はさ、
By the way, when we went horse mackerel fishing...
波と同化しろって言われてよ。
They told me, "Become one with the waves."
海と一体したら釣れた！
And when I became one with the sea, I caught one!
じゃあ今日も波と一体しなよ！早く！
So today, let's become one with the waves too! Hurry!
分かってるよそんなの！
I know that!
ミオヒット!?
Mio hit?!
お、来たかも！わぁ、来たか！来たか！本当に来てんじゃん！
Oh, did it come? Oh! Did it come? Did it come? It's really coming!
来たか!?えっ？
Did it? Eh?
来てないわー！引いてるよ！
It's not coming! It's pulling!
来てないわー！来てなかった。
It's not coming! It wasn't there.
スバルも一回確認してみよ！
Subaru, let's check one more time!
なんか重い荷物付いてる。
It feels like there's a heavy luggage attached.
釣れた!!釣れた!!釣れた!!来いよ、来いよ、来いよ、来いよ、釣れてる、釣れてる！
It caught! It caught! It caught! It's caught! It's caught!
釣れてるよ！やったー！
It caught! Yeah!
うわあ！釣れたよ！釣れてる！
It caught! It's caught!
ミオちゃん釣れるぞここ！
Mio-chan, you can catch them here!
本当に！やっぱり海と一体する事なんや！
Really? So it really is about becoming one with the sea!
今一体してた…？してしてた！
Were you becoming one just now...? You were, you were!
やべえ、釣り好きだな。
Yikes, I love fishing!
ホロライブ釣り部結成しようかな、勝手に。
Hololive Fishing Club, should we establish it on our own?
これ砂の、砂の感じがくんくん来てるのか？
Is this sand, the sand feeling coming in?
私もさ、これ砂かな？とか思って分かんねぇなと思ってた。
I was also like, "Is this sand?" and wondering, but I didn't know.
お、来たかも！お、来てんじゃない？
Ah, did it come? Oh, it came, didn't it?
なんかグイってなった気がする。
I feel like it went "gui" and pulled.
お、来てんって！ミオちゃん頑張って！
Oh, it's coming! Mio-chan, do your best!
マジすか！本当に？でもなんか軽くなったかも！
Really? Really? But it feels lighter!
あ、来て、来て、来て、来て、釣れた！やったー！やったー！
Oh, it's coming! It's coming, it's coming! It's caught! Yay! Yay!
ほら海と一体するのが大事なんだって！取れたー！
"It's important to become one with the sea!" I caught it!
ミオちゃんもう一匹釣ろうぜ！
Mio-chan, let's catch one more!
うん、頑張りたいね！
Yeah, I want to do my best!
どうしよう釣りの案件来たら。
What should we do if a fishing sponsorship comes up?
え、やべえ、来てんのかも。
Oh yikes, is it coming?
来て る？
Is it coming?
逃げられちゃったかな…？
Did it get away...?
でもなんか引いてる…？
But is it pulling something...?
上げてみないと意外とわかんなくない？
If you don't pull it up, you surprisingly won't know.
でしょ？
Right?
まさかの2匹!!
Two of them?!
2匹付いてる！2匹付いてる！
Two are attached! Two are attached!
上げて上げて上げて上げて！看板上げて！
Pull it up, pull it up! Pull up the bumper!
釣れてるような釣れてないようなとか言ったら2匹釣れてた。
It's like it's caught, but like it's not caught—wait, two are caught!
美味そう！
Looks delicious!
え、やべえ、釣れてるかも。
Oh yikes, maybe it's caught!
やべえ、入れ食いや！釣れてる！
Oh yikes, it's hooked! It's caught!
ほら、釣れてる！あ、本当に釣れてる！すごい！
Look, it's caught! Wow, it's caught, amazing!
来て る気がする…！
I feel like it's coming...!
どうだ？どうだ？
How is it? How is it?
来てない…
It's not coming...
あぁ、惜しい。
Aw, too bad.
あのなんか魚って意外に殺意感じ取るらしい。
Apparently fish can surprisingly sense murderous intent.
じゃあウチは殺意が強いってこと？
So you mean your murderous intent is strong...?
確かに。
True.
絶対に釣ってやる…!!
"I'm definitely going to catch you...!!"
なるほどね。
I see.
ミオちゃん今何考えてるの？
Mio-chan, what are you thinking about right now?
えっ？今？
Eh? Right now?
うん。釣りって…なんか無駄だって。
Fishing is... kind of pointless.
いや、そうだよ！これ無駄になりにみんな来てんだもん！
Well that's right, everyone came here just for it to be pointless!
そうなの？
Is that so?
なんか海見てボーとするついでに魚釣ってんだよこれ！
You're fishing while staring at the ocean and spacing out, you know!
そうなんだ。
Is that so?
デジタルデトックスにはもううってつけやね。
It's just right for digital detox.
でしょ？
Right?
波のリズムに身を任せる。
Leave yourself to the rhythm of the waves.
そうだ、波のリズムに身を任せ。
That's right, leave yourself to the rhythm of the waves.
来た！来た！
It came! It came!
きてるきてる！絶対きてると思う！これわ多分、どうだ？
It's coming, it's coming! It's definitely coming, I think! This is probably— How is it?
きてるきてるきてる！きたきた！
It's coming, it's coming, it's coming! It came, it came!
やっぱり来た！やったー！
It really came! Yeah!
やったー！やったー！
Yay! Yay!
ミオちゃん2匹目！
Mio-chan, your second fish!
今の気持ちをどうぞ！
How do you feel right now?
嬉しいです！
I'm happy!
やった！ピチピチです！
Yay! It's flopping!
もう一回ぐらいエントリーしたら帰るか。
If we enter one more time, should we go home?
ハハハ！
Hahaha!
早え！
So fast!
どう？ミオちゃん、体力的に？
How is it, Mio-chan, physically?
全然大丈夫だけど！
I'm totally fine!
本当？走ってる時よりラクだわ。
Really? It's easier than when I'm running.
ふざけんなよ、そんなの！
Don't joke about that!
スバルの大空クルーズが良くないみたい!!
It seems Subaru's open-air cruise isn't going well!!
今日はね、これ釣った魚食べれるから！
Today we can eat the fish we caught!
えっ？キスってさ、どういう種類の食べ方思い浮かぶ？
Eh? Japanese whiting... what kind of ways to eat it come to mind?
天ぷらじゃない？
Tempura, right?
やっぱ天ぷらかな？
You think it's tempura?
お刺身もいけるんだって！
You can also eat it as sashimi!
でっかいからってこと？
Because they're big?
ミオちゃん次のさ、大空クルーズのいけにえ選んで！
Mio-chan, next, choose a victim for the open-air cruise!
えーと、船酔いしなさそうで楽しんでくれそうな人がいい？
Eh? Someone who won't get seasick and seems like they'd enjoy it?
ちはやとかは？
What about Chihaya?
お、ちはやいいじゃん！
Oh, Chihaya's good!
ちは絶対楽しんでくれるでしょ！
Chi would definitely enjoy it!
絶対楽しんでくれそうなタイプ。
She definitely seems like the type to enjoy it.
じゃあちはに一言！
So a word for Chi!
意外と酔うから絶対に酔い止めは飲んできた方がいいよ。
You get carsick easily, so you should definitely take seasickness medicine.
ちはやバイク乗ってるの、バイクだっけ車だっけ？
Chihaya rides a bike—is it a bike or a car?
車！
A car!
酔わないんじゃないの、意外に？えー、どうかな～？
She might not get carsick, I wonder?
ちは！来年乗ってくれよな！
Chi! You better ride with us next year!
今年でも可！
This year is fine too!
でもノリノリで来てくれそう！
But she'd probably come with high energy!
鬼ノリいいからな！
She has great energy, after all!
えでも莉々華とかも良さそう！
And Ririka seems good too!
莉々華はさ、なんかもう何が起きるか分んないからさ。
Ririka... with her, you never know what's going to happen.
なんか莉々華と行くんだったらなんかスゲェの釣りに行きたいな。
If I go with Ririka, I feel like I'd go on some crazy fishing trip.
あー、なるほどね。
Ah, I see.
でもフブキもめっちゃ釣り好きだからさ。
But Fubuki really loves fishing too, so...
そうなの？
Is that so?
そうだよ！だってことあるごとにゲーム内で釣りばっしてるじゃん。
That's right, because whenever something happens, she's always fishing in the game.
いや、確かに。あれゲームだからとかじゃなくて？
Well, that's true, but not just because it's a game—
違うよ～！
No way!
でも確かに釣りガチャ要素強いしな！
Though fishing gacha elements are strong, for sure!
今日めちゃ晴れてよかったね。
It's so sunny and wonderful today!
ねえ、すごいよ。
Yeah, it's amazing.
こんなにバチバチに晴れて。
To be this bright and clear.
の?
What?
ずれてんじゃん！
You drifted off!
どうだどうだ！
No way, no way!
どうだ！重い気がする！
No way, I really feel it!
みおちゃんデカいの来計んじゃん！
Mio-chan, it's huge!
どうだどうだ！
No way, no way!
釣れたか？
Did you catch it?
釣れた！
I caught it!
やったー！
Yay!
元気いっぱいだー
So energetic!
うわ、クラゲだ！
Oh, a jellyfish!
すごい浮いてる！
It's floating so high!
本当だ！
Really!
そうなの？持って帰る？
You want to bring it home?
いや、要らない…
No way, no...
怖いゃん！
That's scary!
刺されるといてぇ
It hurts if it stings you!
やべえ、これ釣れてる多分。
Oh crap, this one's caught too, probably.
来て るか？
Is it coming?
引いてる引いてる！
It's pulling, it's pulling!
これは絶対釣れてる！
This one's definitely caught!
おらー！
Come on!
キター！
Got it!
やったー！
Yay!
俺がエントリーしたい！
I want to enter, too!
いいよ。
Okay.
行くよ。
Here we go.
いち！
One...
にの！
Two...
さん！
Three!
おせぇ…
So slow...
言うの忘れてたなって今！
I forgot to say it just now!
果たして釣れるのか。
I wonder if it'll get caught.
「ちょん」としました！
"It nudged!"
あとはミオちゃん頑張って。
Alright, Mio-chan, do your best.
「ちょん」ってするの分かるんだ！
You can tell when it nudges?
うん。
Yeah.
引いてる…？
Is it pulling...?
引いてる！
Wait, it's pulling!
嘘っ！
For real?
本当だ引いてる！
Wait, it's pulling, it's pulling!
引いてる引いてる！
It's pulling, it's pulling!
なんか引いてる！
Something's pulling!
ゆっくりゆっくり…
Slowly, slowly...
ゆっくり、なんか引いてるかも！
Slowly, I think it's pulling!
がんばれ！
You can do it!
釣れた！
Got it!
引け引け引け！
Pull, pull, pull!
うわぁー！
Whoa!
ラストフィッシング！
Last fishing!
やったー！
Yay!
という事で！
And with that...
本日の釣果がこちら！
Here is our catch for today!
うわぁー！
Whoa!
すっごいよミオちゃんマジで！
That's amazing, Mio-chan, seriously!
シロギス14匹フィニッシュ！
A 14 shirogisu finish!
やったー！
Yay!
という事でミオちゃん、
So, Mio-chan...
釣ったやつ、すぐ食べたいと思わないか？
Don't you want to eat the fish you caught right away?
おー！
Oh?
た、食べれるんですか？
Can we eat them?
生は無理だよ？うち。
Raw is impossible, right?
いやいや生で行けとは言ってないよ！
I didn't say we'd eat them raw!
このままはちょっと踊り食いはね…
Well, eating them raw is a bit...
狼といえど！
Though I did say that!
これからこれを料理して！
From here, we'll cook them...
食べたいと思います！
And eat them!
おー、楽しみ！
Yay, I can't wait!
という事で！
So...
さっき釣った魚がこちらです！
Here is the fish we caught earlier!
えー！すごい！
Whoa, amazing!
もう面影ない！
There's no trace of them left!
いやそうだよ！
Well, exactly!
完全にない！
Completely gone!
という事でね！
And so, yeah.
釣った後はやっぱ、釣りたての魚を食べるというのが醍醐味！
Eating freshly caught fish is the real thrill!
うわっ、贅沢！
So luxurious!
食べようぜ！
Let's dig in!
せーの！
Ready...
いただきます！
Itadakimasu!
え、何から食べる？
What are you eating first?
えっ、お刺身でしょやっぱ！
Sashimi, obviously!
お刺身にできるぐらいのデカいやって珍しいらしいよ！
Getting big ones that can be made into sashimi...
そうなの？
Is that so?
いただきます。
Itadakimasu.
いただきます！
Itadakimasu!
天ぷらも食べよう。
Let's eat the tempura, too.
うん。
Yeah.
天ぷら天ぷら！
Tempura, tempura!
いただきます！
Itadakimasu!
うまっ！
Delicious!
うまい！
Amazing!
これはうまい！
This is delicious!
でしょ！
Right?
でしょってスバルが作ったわけじゃないんですけど。
Not that Subaru made it, though!
作っていただいたんですけど最高です！
It was made for us, but it's the best!
ミオちゃんどうだった？
How was it, Mio-chan?
大空クルーズ星3って言ってたやん。
You said Oozora Cruise was 3 stars!
なんと今ならこのプロの人が作ったご飯付き！
And now, with a meal made by a professional included...
そんなん星5になるに決まってるじゃん！
That's bound to be 5 stars!
いぇーい！
Yay!
それではこのご飯を食べながら
So while we eat this meal...
最後は「さよなら」したいと思うんだけど
We want to say goodbye at the end, but...
もう「さよなら」のお時間なんですか？
Is it already time to say goodbye?
そうだよ！
That's right!
今日は海上保安庁さんに行ってさ、
We went to the Japan Coast Guard, and...
いや、そうだよ朝から！
Yeah, that's right, since morning!
超早朝からさ、行ってさ、ルールを教えてもらってさ、
Right from the very beginning, they taught us the rules...
大空クルーズが出航してさ、釣ってさ、これ作ってもらってさ、
Oozora Cruise set sail, we fished, and had this made for us...
ちょっと聞いてる？食べてるけど。
Are you listening while eating?!
それじゃあ！
Well then!
大空クルーズこれにて第一部終！
That concludes part one of Oozora Cruise!
じゃあみんな、またねー！ばいばーい！
See you everyone, bye-bye!
ご来場…？なんていうの？
Wait, arrival...?
船に乗れー！ばいばーい！
Get on the ship! Bye-bye!
次はお前だ！！
You're next!!